<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Articles on Aiman Ismail</title><link>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/</link><description>Recent content in Articles on Aiman Ismail</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 02:05:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pokgak.xyz/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Access internal kubernetes services from anywhere using Tailscale</title><link>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/k8s-cluster-access-tailscale/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 02:05:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/k8s-cluster-access-tailscale/</guid><description>I recently setup a local kubernetes in my home network to play with and one of the issues that I faced is that it is hard to access the services inside the cluster from my laptop. I don&amp;rsquo;t have a load-balancer in my setup so everytime I want to access a service from my laptop, I&amp;rsquo;ll have to run kubectl port-forward first before using the localhost address to access it.</description></item><item><title>On Public Speaking</title><link>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/on-public-speaking/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 21:37:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/on-public-speaking/</guid><description>I had the chance to give a talk at my local DevOps meetup last July and recently, did another one at a Tech Talk event hosted by my current employer. Both talks are related to OPA but this blog post will be more of a personal reflection for me just to document these moments in my career.
There are two common things that I noticed about myself from giving the talk and I&amp;rsquo;m gonna describe them here.</description></item><item><title>Interview Series: Explain How Kubernetes DNS works</title><link>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/explain-k8s-dns/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2023 23:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/explain-k8s-dns/</guid><description>This will be the first in my interview questions series. I&amp;rsquo;ll compile interesting questions that I got from my experience interviewing for DevOps/SRE role in Malaysia.
Calling a service by its cluster-internal DNS We&amp;rsquo;ll go from the highest to the lowest level in this journey. So let&amp;rsquo;s go through the scenario a bit: you have two services, foo and bar. those two services live in the same namespace app in your cluster.</description></item><item><title>Instrumenting CI Pipelines using otel-cli</title><link>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/instrument-your-ci/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Apr 2023 12:18:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/instrument-your-ci/</guid><description>Why? Why not? Get the whole picture of what is happening in your pipeline. Get notified when something is taking longer than it should.
How? Use otel-cli, a standalone Go binary that can create OpenTelemetry traces and sends to a tracing backend using the OTLP protocol.
OpenTelemetry? https://opentelemetry.io/
Tracing Backend? You collect traces from your application using the OpenTelemetry SDK. To visualize the relationship between the traces, you&amp;rsquo;ll have to send the traces to a tracing backend, which will provide a UI for exploring your traces.</description></item><item><title>How to use OPA policy from an S3 bucket when using Atlantis policy check</title><link>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/conftest-pull-from-s3/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 22:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/conftest-pull-from-s3/</guid><description>Atlantis is an application used for collaborating on a Terraform code base using pull requests and one of the feature that it has is to run conftest and test a set of defined OPA policies. At the moment I&amp;rsquo;m writing this article, Atlantis only supports using local sources i.e. local filesystem as the source of the policy. In this article, I&amp;rsquo;ll show an example of how to use an S3 bucket instead as the source for the policies.</description></item><item><title>Getting started with OPA and conftest</title><link>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/opa-conftest/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2022 13:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/opa-conftest/</guid><description>I started using OPA at my $dayJob recently and there are some parts that I think is not intuitive to grok for beginners.
If you want to play around with the rules and input, you can use the Rego Playground. It&amp;rsquo;s super useful and I used it to test out policies and test my hypothesis when playing around with Rego language.
How does OPA, Rego, and conftest related to each other?</description></item><item><title>Instrumenting a Slack bot with OpenTelemetry</title><link>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/otel-slack-integration/</link><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 17:43:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/otel-slack-integration/</guid><description>Note: I&amp;rsquo;m using pseudocode in the code example in this article to keep the article brief. Please refer to the official Slack and OpenTelemetry documentation for the actual code.
I&amp;rsquo;ve talked about the basics of OpenTelemetry in my previous article. In this one, I&amp;rsquo;ll explain more on how we&amp;rsquo;re integrating OpenTelemetry with our Slack-based application.
At the end of this article, this is roughly how the span lifetime and events created will look like:</description></item><item><title>OpenTelemetry Basics</title><link>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/otel-basics/</link><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 17:43:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/otel-basics/</guid><description>I got to work on integrating OpenTelemetry in an application that our team maintains recently so I&amp;rsquo;m starting a series documenting my learnings throughout this journey.
A little background info on the application I&amp;rsquo;m working on: it&amp;rsquo;s a Slack chatbot written in Typescript using BoltJS. Our goal is to know how many users are using our Slack bot with a breakdown of the percentage of successful and error interactions. When an error happened, we also want to know what exactly the user did and the current state of the application that caused it to error.</description></item><item><title>Terraform modules: be opinionated</title><link>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/terraform-modules-opinionated/</link><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 17:43:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/terraform-modules-opinionated/</guid><description>Modules are containers for multiple resources that are used together.
Terraform modules is a way to bundle a bunch of Terraform resources into one group. Although not explicitly mentioned in the definition, it is also a way to provide an abstraction to the resources inside the module and only expose inputs and outputs that are relevant to the users of the module.
Terraform Module as an Abstraction Layer A Terraform resource usually tends to be generic in that it allows you to configure it multiple ways through the input variables that it can accept.</description></item><item><title>Generate fail HCL menggunakan library hclwrite</title><link>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/hclwrite-basics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Sep 2021 12:25:34 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/hclwrite-basics/</guid><description>HCL adalah bahasa yang digunakan dalam produk-produk daripada Hashicorp seperti Terraform dan Packer. Kebiasaannya, fail HCL ini ditulis secara manual tetapi jika anda ingin menulis atau mengubah fail-fail tersebut secara programmatik menggunakan code, maka anda boleh menggunakan hclwrite, sebuah library yang ditulis dalam Go.
Blog post ini dibahagikan kepada dua bahagian. Bahagian pertama menunjukkan cara untuk menghasilkan block baru from scratch dan simpan ke fail. Ini adalah asas untuk bahagian kedua di mana kita akan mengubah fail HCL sedia ada dan memastikan format fail tersebut terjaga dan tidak melakukan pengubahan secara semberono.</description></item><item><title>Auto-update Graf Covid-19 menggunakan Github Actions</title><link>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/auto-update-citf-graphs/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 09:56:10 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/auto-update-citf-graphs/</guid><description>Dalam blog post saya sebelum ini saya dah menerangkan bagaimana saya membuat graf animasi perkembangan status pemberian imunisasi negeri-negeri di Malaysia. Seterusnya saya juga ada berkongsi asas-asas untuk menggunakan Github Actions. Dalam blog post ini saya ingin menerangkan pula bagaimana saya menggunakan Github Actions untuk mengemaskini graf tersebut dengan data terbaru yang dikeluarkan oleh pihak CITF Malaysia secara automatik setiap hari.
Konfigurasi penuh Sebelum saya mula penerangan, inilah hasil fail workflow Github Actions yang saya gunakan:</description></item><item><title>Apa itu Cloud Computing?</title><link>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/cloud-computing/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 23:47:19 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/cloud-computing/</guid><description>Perkataan &amp;ldquo;cloud&amp;rdquo; rasanya tak asing lagi dalam kamus anak muda zaman sekarang tapi kebanyakannya merujuk kepada &amp;ldquo;cloud storage&amp;rdquo; iaitu servis penyimpanan data online. Kali ini saya ingin menerangkan konsep cloud computing dari sudut seorang programmer.
Apa itu cloud? &amp;lsquo;The cloud is just someone else&amp;rsquo;s computer&amp;rsquo;, adalah salah satu meme yang banyak ditemui online. Hakikatnya begitulah, gambar yang diupload ke iCloud, website Twitter yang anda akses setiap hari, video yang anda tonton di YouTube, semuanya dilayan (hosted) oleh komputer-komputer yang tersusun di data center besar di seluruh dunia.</description></item><item><title>Animasi interaktif berdasarkan data CITF menggunakan Plotly</title><link>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/graf-interaktif-citf-plotly/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 04:59:55 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/graf-interaktif-citf-plotly/</guid><description>Saya gemar melayari subreddit r/dataisbeautiful dan melihat graf hasil buatan pengguna Reddit lain di sana. Salah satu jenis graf yang saya paling minat adalah apabila graf itu seolah-olah animasi, berubah selaras mengikut jangka masa waktu yang semakin bertambah. Kita boleh melihat perkembangan sesuatu data itu dari mula hingga ke akhir.
Contoh post terbaru di subreddit itu yang mempunyai graf sebegini adalah seperti graf di bawah yang memaparkan Kadar vaksinasi sebahagian daripada negara-negara di seluruh dunia (sayang Malaysia tidak dimasukkan sekali di sini):</description></item><item><title>Pengenalan Github Actions</title><link>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/pengenalan-github-actions/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2021 04:49:42 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://pokgak.xyz/articles/pengenalan-github-actions/</guid><description>Github Actions (GA) adalah servis automation yang ditawarkan oleh Github untuk semua penggunanya. Jika anda mempunyai repository public di Github, anda boleh mula menggunakan Github Actions pada saat ini tanpa perlu membayar apa-apa pun!
Bagaimana untuk mula dengan Github Actions? Untuk mula menggunakan Github Actions, anda boleh pergi ke mana-mana repository public yang anda miliki dan seterusnya pergi ke tab Actions.
Jika anda belum pernah setup mana-mana workflow di repository tersebut, anda akan melihat pilihan templates siap yang boleh digunakan untuk pelbagai jenis projek.</description></item></channel></rss>